Guide to the Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning BCMS.0039
Brooklyn Collection
- Brooklyn welfare and health councils, 1931-1957
  - Neighborhood council files, 1944-1957
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Hospital: Reports and reference material (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Maria Lawton Center for Older People [formerly Stuyvesant Center for Older People], 1952-1955 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Stuyvesant Community Center: Correspondence and minutes, 1946-1957 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Stuyvesant Community Center: Correspondence and minutes, 1944-1945 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Youth Council (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Bensonhurst: Bensonhurst Child Care Center (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Boro Park: Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Brooklyn Heights: Brooklyn Heights Association (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Boy's Club: Correspondence and related material, 1950-1956 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Neighborhood Council: Correspondence, memos, minutes, 1938-1952 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Boy's Club: Press clippings (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council (of the Welfare and Health Council of NYC): Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Blood donors (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Dental, 1950-1952 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Diabetics Committee, 1949-1951 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Entertainment, 1949-1951 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Executive Committee: Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Fundraising (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Mental Health Committee: Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Meetings, 1948-1952 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Related materials, 1948-1957 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: New Junior High School Committee (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Nominating Committee (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Press clippings (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Publicity and Membership Committee (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Recreation Committee (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Reports (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Health Council: Sanitation Committee: Correspondence (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Neighborhood Council: Correspondence, 1947-1953 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Neighborhood Health and Welfare Council: Correspondence, 1953 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Neighborhood Health and Welfare Council: Correspondence, 1954 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Neighborhood Health and Welfare Council: Correspondence, 1955 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Brownsville: Brownsville Neighborhood Health and Welfare Council: Correspondence, 1956 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Brownsville: Miscellaneous (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Canarsie: Breukelen Housing Project Community Center (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Canarsie: General: Press clippings (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Community Council (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Bylaws (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Committee on Health of the School Child (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: General correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Mental health projects (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Diabetes projects (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Monthly activities (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Press clippings (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: Sanitation Committee (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Canarsie: Canarsie Health Council: X-ray Survey Committee (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Clinton Hill: Miscellaneous (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Coney Island: General (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Coney Island: Press clippings (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Cooper Park Houses: Cooper Park Day Care Committee (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Crown Heights: General (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Crown Heights: Eastern Parkway: Crown Heights Inter-Group Council (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Downtown Brooklyn: General (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - East New York: Boulevard Community Center (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - East New York: Boulevard Housing Project Summer Day Camp (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - East New York: Boulevard Nursery School (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - East New York: General (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - East New York: East New York/Brownsville Health Council (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - East New York: East New York/Brownsville Health Council (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - East New York: East New York/Brownsville Health Council: Monthly reports (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - East New York: Press clippings (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - East New York: East New York Youth and Adult Center (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Fort Greene: Fort Greene District Civic Association (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Fort Greene: Press clippings (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Fort Greene: District Health Committee (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Fort Greene: Fort Greene Recreation Project, Julius Samuels, New York School for Social Work, 1946 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Glenwood: Glenwood Community Center and Recreation Project (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Glenwood: Glenwood Community Center (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Gowanus: Gowanus Community Center (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Gravesend: General (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Greenpoint: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Manhattan Beach: General (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Highland Park: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Kensington: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Midwood: General (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Mill Basin: General (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Navy Yard District: Navy Yard District Neighborhood Council (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Navy Yard District: Navy Yard District Neighborhood Council: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Prospect Park: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Red Hook: Old South Brooklyn Youth Council Project (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - Red Hook: Old South Brooklyn Youth Council Project: Student diaries, 1947-1948 (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - Red Hook: Red Hook Community Association (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Red Hook: Red Hook – Gowanus District Health Committee (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - Sheepshead Bay: General (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - Sheepshead Bay: Press clippings (Box 33, Folder 17)
    - South Brooklyn: NYC Youth Board Project (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - South Brooklyn: NYC Youth Board Reports, 1952 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - South Marlboro: South Marlboro Community Council (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - Williamsburg: General (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Williamsburg: Jewish Association for Neighborhood Centers (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Williamsburg: Press clippings (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Williamsburg: Williamsburg Neighborhood Council Youth Division (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Williamsburg: Williamsburg Neighborhood Council (Box 34, Folder 5)
- Related government agencies, 1938-57 [bulk 1950-1957]; 1950-1957
  All subseries are arranged alphabetically by agency name.
  - New York City agencies, 1948-57 [bulk 1954-1957]
    Arranged by city agency, these files contain press clippings, reports, publications and some correspondence with various units of city government, including the New York City Youth Board, regarding prevention and control of juvenile delinquency; Board of Estimate, regarding budgets; the committee on Inter-group relations, the Mayor's Committee on Unity, and the Board of Education, on school integration; Health Department, regarding summer day camp, day care, and tuberculosis screening in Bedford-Stuyvesant; Housing Authority, regarding public housing projects; and the New York Police Department, regarding the Police Athletic League (PAL), and the Juvenile Aid Bureau. Also included are files on the Community Mental Health Board, Domestic Relations Court; Welfare Department; and the Department of Hospitals.
    - General: Press clippings (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Board of Estimate (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Budget (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - City Planning, Department of (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Civil Service (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Commission on Intergroup Relations (COIR) (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Community Mental Health Board (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Domestic Relations Court (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Education, Board of: Budget Request, 1956-1957 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Education, Board of: Bureau of Child Guidance (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Education, Board of: Bureau of Community Education (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Education, Board of: Commission on Integration (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Education, Board of: Correspondence and reports (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Education, Board of: Press clippings (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Education, Board of: Annual reports (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Education, Board of: Publications: "The Three R's Plus" (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Education, Board of: Publications: Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Education, Board of: Publications: Vocational Training (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Health Department of: Bulletins and reports (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Health Department of: Correspondence (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Health Department of: Day Camp (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - Health Department of: Day Care (Box 35, Folder 14)
    - Health Department of: Press clippings (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - Health Department of: Target TB Bedford project (Box 35, Folder 16)
    - Hospitals, Department of (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - Housing Authority (Box 35, Folder 18)
    - Housing Authority: Reports (Box 35, Folder 19)
    - Mayor's Committee on Unity (Box 35, Folder 20)
    - Parks, Department of (Box 35, Folder 21)
    - Police Department: Coordinating Councils (Box 35, Folder 22)
    - Police Department: Juvenile Aid Bureau (Box 35, Folder 23)
    - Police Department: Police Athletic League (Box 35, Folder 24)
    - Police Department: Reports (Box 35, Folder 25)
    - Welfare, Department of: Correspondence and reports (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Welfare, Department of: Day care division (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Welfare, Department of: Department organization (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Welfare, Department of: General information pamphlets (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Welfare, Department of: Press clippings (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Welfare, Department of: Social Audit System (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Youth Board: Brooklyn Gang Project: Correspondence (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Youth Board: Brooklyn Gang Project: Committee to Draft "Eagle" Article (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Youth Board: Central Registration Project: Report, 1952 March (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Youth Board: Brooklyn Advisory Committee for the Council of Social and Athletic Clubs (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Youth Board: Correspondence (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Youth Board of Council of Social and Athletic Clubs: Report, 1952 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Youth Board: Press clippings (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Youth Board: Publications: General (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Youth Board: Publications: "Youth Board News" (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Youth Board: South Brooklyn Project (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Youth Board: Williamsburg Demonstration Project on Volunteers (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - New York State agencies, 1950-1957
    This rather miscellaneous collection of limited correspondence, reports, newsletters, and publications includes the state departments of Commerce, Education, Health, Housing, Mental Health, Parole, Social Welfare, and Youth an Delinquency. Also included is material on a Temporary Commission to simplify the court system (1955); the Commission Against Discrimination, and labor market development reports.
    - Commerce, Department of (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Courts, Temporary Commission on the (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Discrimination, Commission Against: Brooklyn Human Relations Conference (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Discrimination, Commission Against: Newsletter (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Discrimination, Commission Against: Reports and publications (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Education Department: Adult Education (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Health, Department of (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Housing, Division of (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Labor, Department of: Labor Market Development Reports, August 1956 – April 1957 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Labor, Department of: Labor Market Development Reports, June 1957 – October 1957 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Labor, Department of: Reports and correspondence (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Mental Hygiene, Department of (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Parole, Division of (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Social Welfare, Department of (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Youth and Delinquency, Temporary State Commission on (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Youth Commission (Box 38, Folder 12)
  - Federal agencies, circa 1938-1956 [includes undated material]
    This subseries includes a Department of Defense brochure on nuclear fallout protection; Korean War era Veterans Administration material; and pamphlets on health issues, forms, guidelines and limited correspondence with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
    - Health, Education and Welfare, Department of [formerly Federal Security Agency] (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Veterans' Administration (Box 38, Folder 14)
- Related non-government agencies, 1937-1957 [bulk 1945-1957]; 1945-1957
  - Brooklyn College, 1945-1957
    Correspondence between BCSP staff and various faculty and staff members at Brooklyn College reveal the close relationship between the two, as BCSP staff were recruited to speak to students on topics relating to community organization and social work, as well as encouraging students to be involved as volunteers (see General correspondence, 1945-57). Louise Simsar, Executive Secretary of BCSP served on the College's Advisory Placement Committee (see committee correspondence, 1948-56), which explored vocational opportunities for college students in business and professional fields, especially the increased need for employees in service occupations. Also included are press clippings and several Brooklyn College publications.
    - Advisory Placement Committee (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1945-1952 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Press clippings and publications (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn Public Library, 1950-1957
    The Brooklyn Public Library was a member of BCSP, and collaborated with BCSP on projects for the Puerto Rican community; a directory of summer recreation services; and a bibliography of books and materials for new social service workers entitled "Getting acquainted with Brooklyn." Correspondence includes letters about and minutes of the Committee for Brooklyn Public Library Week (1953), and acknowledgments for BCSP publications contributed to the library. Also included are press clippings and several BPL publications and flyers.
    - Correspondence (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Press clippings (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Publications and flyers (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - The Greater New York Fund, 1937-1957 [bulk 1952-1957]
    Organized in 1936-37, the Greater New York Fund (GNYF) began operation in 1938, and served to solicit contributions from businesses and employee groups for distribution to over four hundred New York City health and welfare agencies, including voluntary hospitals, services for children and the aged, and health care services. This subseries includes a report on tentative plans for the founding of the Fund (1937); correspondence with BCSP regarding GNYF activities, fundraising and contributions from BCSP (1946-57); sample applications for participation in the fund, press clippings, and GNYF pamphlets, flyers and newsletters. A 1948 GNYF report of the Sub-Committee to Study the Problem of Imbalance of Services in New York with Special Reference to Borough Imbalance, includes detailed statistical and census information on population, socio-economic status, housing, economic factors, health care, children's services, delinquency, and education. Also included are reports on the distribution of family services, health care services, group work and recreation services, the care of children, and services for the aged.
    - Areas of solicitation and information re: agency participation (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and fundraising campaign information, 1946-1952 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and fundraising campaign information, 1953-1957 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Founding "Foreword on Tentative Plan for a Community Fund in NYC", 1937 December 30 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Press clippings (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlets, flyers and newsletters (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Report of the Sub-Committee to Study the Imbalance of Services Among the Boroughs, part 1 of 2, 1948 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Report of the Sub-Committee to Study the Imbalance of Services Among the Boroughs, part 2 of 2, 1948 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Urban League of Greater New York, 1942-1957 [bulk 1946-1957]
    Alphabetical by topic.
    Founded 1910, the Urban League of Greater New York, was an affiliate of the National Urban League, the oldest and largest American interracial social service agency. It was a member of the Welfare and Health Council of New York City and a participant in (i.e., funded by) the Greater New York Fund. The Urban League's stated mission was to win equal opportunity for all Americans in employment, housing (it opposed slum clearance and housing projects), education, and health and welfare services. Its programs were historically centered on African-Americans; during the period covered here, it began to expand its programs to include Puerto Ricans as well. The material in this subseries includes correspondence and related material regarding BCSP's participation in Urban League programs including the Urban League's Group Work Advisory Committee (1947-49), and the Brooklyn Coordinating Committee on Fair Housing (1956-57), which advocated the New York State Metcalf-Baker bills and housing desegregation. Also included are press clippings, and Urban League publications and newsletters.
    - Advisory Committee on Group work: Correspondence, reports, related material, 1947-1949 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Brooklyn Coordinating Committee for Fair Housing: Correspondence and related material, 1956-1957 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, reports, misc, AYZ, 1946-1957 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Press clippings (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Publications, newsletters (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Report, "Aspects of Negro Life", 1947 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Subcommittee on Personal Service: Correspondence, reports, and related material, 1946-1947 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Other related agencies, circa 1948-1957 [includes undated material]
    Alphabetical by organization name.
    Subseries 7.5 is comprised of files on over 250 wide ranging voluntary agencies, schools and school groups, civic associations, religious social service agencies, business and professional organizations, local chapters of national social welfare organizations, and YM/YWCAs and YM/YWHAs. Contents of the files vary, but generally include information about the organization, its purpose and programs; press clippings; and limited correspondence with BCSP. Organizations represented by more substantial files include Citizens for AllDay Neighborhood Schools; American Jewish Congress; Association for the Help of Retarded Children, Inc.; Association of American Social Workers; Brooklyn Association for Mental Hygiene, Inc.; Brooklyn Child Guidance League; Brooklyn Jewish Community Council; Brooklyn Juvenile Protection Agency; Brooklyn Museum; Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association, Inc.; Citizens Committee for Children of New York City; Citizens' Housing and Planning Council of New York, Inc.; National Publicity Council for Health and Welfare Services, Inc.; New York CIO Council; Community Association of School Districts 25 and 27; and Youth for Better Citizens of Tomorrow.
    - A: Miscellaneous (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Abraham and Straus [A&S] (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Adult Education Association of the USA (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Action [American Council to Improve our Neighborhoods] (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Adelphi College (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - AFL, Local 808 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - All-Day Neighborhood Schools, Citizens for the (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - American Association for the United Nations, Ltd. (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - American Cancer Society (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - American Group Psychotherapy Association (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - American Jewish Committee: Brooklyn Division NY Chapter (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - American Jewish Congress (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - American Legion: Youth Affairs (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - American Orthopsychiatric Association, Inc. (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - American Public Welfare Association (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - American Red Cross (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - American Social Hygiene Association (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - American Theater Wing (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - Americans for Democratic Action (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - [New York] Amsterdam News (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - Angel Guardian Home, Brooklyn (Box 41, Folder 21)
    - Aperion Men's Club, Brooklyn (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - Apostate for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - Arthritis and Rheumatism Foundation (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - Assembly of Jewish Women's Organizations (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children (Box 41, Folder 26)
    - Association for the Help of Retarded Children, Inc. (Box 41, Folder 27)
    - Association for the Study of Community Organizations [ASCO] (Box 41, Folder 28)
    - Association for the Study of Community Organizations [ASCO] (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Association of American Social Workers: Legislative Committee (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Association of Brooklyn Settlements (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Anthonian Hall (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Aunt Gertrude Sunshine Fund (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - B: Miscellaneous (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Bankers Club of Brooklyn (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Bay Community Club (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Beach Haven Jewish Center (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Bedford-Clinton Community Schools Council (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Beth-El Hospital (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Big Brother Movement (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Big Sister League, Inc. (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Blue Star Mothers (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - B'nai Brith Brooklyn Heights (Box 42, Folder 15)
    - Boy Scouts of America (Box 42, Folder 16)
    - Boy's Athletic League (Box 42, Folder 17)
    - Boy's Clubs of America (Box 42, Folder 18)
    - Boy's Welcome Hall (Box 42, Folder 19)
    - Brook Borough Club (Box 42, Folder 20)
    - Brooklyn: General (Box 42, Folder 21)
    - Brooklyn Organizations: Miscellaneous (Box 42, Folder 22)
    - Brooklyn Amateur Baseball Foundation (Box 42, Folder 23)
    - Brooklyn Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor [AICP] (Box 42, Folder 24)
    - Brooklyn Association for Mental Health, Inc. (Box 42, Folder 25)
    - Brooklyn Association for the Rehabilitation of Offenders (Box 42, Folder 26)
    - Brooklyn Bar Association (Box 42, Folder 27)
    - Brooklyn Benevolent Society (Box 42, Folder 28)